You would prefer the human race to
endure, right?
>> Uh,
>> you're hesitating.
>> Well, I Yes.
>> I don't know. I I would
>> This is Peter Teal.
>> This is a long hesitation. So many
hesitation.
>> There's so many questions and questions.
>> Should the human race survive?
>> Uh, yes. Okay. But
>> he's been a major player in Silicon
Valley for a long, long time.
>> I'm Peter Teal. I build companies and I
support people who are building new
things from social networks to rocket
ships.
>> You might know him as the
multi-billionaire who co-founded PayPal
and Palanteer. As Facebook's first
outside investor, [music] the guy who
funds out there projects like floating
countries, private space travel, and the
quest for immortality. Peter Teal
rejects the idea that death is
inevitable. He wants to transform
humanity.
Transhumanism was this radical
transformation where your human natural
body gets transformed into an immortal
body. We want you to be able to change
your heart and change your mind and
change your whole your whole body.
>> But he also wants to change something
else. For decades, Teal has schemed from
the shadows to reshape American
politics. Tonight, I urge all of my
fellow Americans to stand up and vote
for Donald Trump.
>> He bankrolled Trump's first campaign. He
turbocharged JD Vance's career. Teal
openly questions the democratic system,
and he's declared that to him, freedom
is incompatible with democracy. His
vision of an ideal society sounds more
like an oligarchy, a country ruled by a
few powerful rich people, or even just
one. Today, his influence is rapidly
expanding across the world. From the
beginning of his career, he's been
building tools to rewire how power
works. Palunteer, his brainchild,
enables intelligence agencies and
militaries to anticipate their enemy's
next move before it's made. Maybe even
your next move, too.
None of this happened by accident. Peter
Teio plays the long game. He's patiently
planned his moves for decades, always
several steps ahead. So, what does Peter
Tio actually want? What's his problem
with democracy?
And is there an end game?
>> This video is largely based on the
research collected in The Contrarian:
Peter Teal and Silicon Valley's Pursuit
of Power by Max Chefkin. You'll find a
link in the description.
>> [music]
>> New York City, 2010. A TV show has set
up a night for Peter Teal to meet Gary
Kasparov, one of the greatest chess
players of all time. Teal and Kasparov
have met before and get along well. They
like chatting about politics,
technology, and of course, chess. Peter
Teal's a diehard chess fan. In fact,
he's a national chess master. He's
admired the Grandmaster Kasparov since
he was a teenager and the respect is
mutual. Kasparov admires Teiel's
intelligence and business sense is one
of the probably most successful
entrepreneurs of his generation. He is
very aggressively investing. He looks
for the future.
>> Teal's legendary status in business is
hard to overstate. His companies have
created technologies that have changed
the course of the modern world. and his
influence helped define tech, an
industry that has produced millions of
jobs and trillions of dollars of wealth.
That night, Kasparov and Teal hit up a
chess club. Teal plays a game of speed
chess with the owner and wins.
>> I'm totally embarrassed.
>> You're embarrassed as well. [laughter]
>> Kasparov suggests his chess skills are
probably why Teal is such a successful
businessman and why he tends to hire
chess players for his companies.
>> That's why he's hiring chess players.
You know, Peter just told me the story
then when they had his the IPO for
PayPal. So, he did a simo for 10
employees of PayPal.
>> And sure, TL is probably on to
something. Chess skills transfer well
into the world of business. It's a game
of strategy where it pays off to think
several moves ahead. Skills that don't
hurt in politics either.
Sometime after this evening, Kasparov
and Teal drift apart. Maybe the two
don't have that much in common after
all. It's not just that the Russian
Kasparov is a way better chess player.
He's also one of the world's most
prominent pro-democracy activists. He's
a major thorn in Putin's [music] sight,
tirelessly campaigning for a freer
Russia.
>> So, I'm fighting to restore democracy in
my country.
>> Trump potential victory uh could
threaten not only democracy in this
country, but you know, democracy
worldwide.
>> And Peter Teio, well, kind of the
opposite trajectory. Critics warn he's
emerging as a major threat to American
democracy.
Billionaires like Teal reshaping
politics is terrifying. [music]
Connecting to airport Wi-Fi ranks way
lower on the scale. But having your data
floating around unprotected online is a
threat you can actually do something
about. This is where today's sponsor,
NordVPN, [music] comes in. NordVPN
encrypts your internet traffic so your
personal data stays private. With the
shopping season in full swing, think
twice before clicking that deal that
[music] looks too good to be true. It
can happen to anyone. Regular VPNs don't
always protect you against fake web
stores. NordVPN's threat protection pro
helps you avoid malware, hackers, and
trackers, even when you're not connected
to a VPN. It's a certified anti-ishing
tool recognized by leading cyber
security labs. Try NordVPN risk-free
with a 30-day money back guarantee, and
go to nordvpn.com/fernv
for a huge discount plus four extra
months. You can also scan this QR code
or check the link in the description.
Wait, did you actually just scan that QR
code?
Peter Teal is around 8 years old when
his family arrives in Swakupmmont, a
former German colony on Namibia's coast.
He moved here with his parents and
brother after some years in Ohio. During
the 1970s, the city is occupied by a
parttheid South Africa. At the time,
it's a town clinging to its German
[music] roots, where Hitler's birthday
is still celebrated, and the Nazi salute
is a casual greeting for some. Peter's
father, Klaus, takes an engineering job
at a uranium mine just outside town.
[music] The mine is controversial and
shrouded in secrecy. According to
international law, South Africa isn't
allowed to mine here, but they go ahead
anyway, extracting Namibia's uranium as
part of South Africa's nuclear weapons
program. The regime is secretly
developing bombs to defend against a
possible Soviet attack and to protect
the apartheite way of life. According to
a former British activist group, black
laborers have worked at the mine under
dangerous conditions. Meanwhile, white
families like the Teals enjoy a
privileged life. Brand new medical
facilities, country club memberships,
kids and private school. Young Peter is
reportedly first put in a whites only
school in Johannesburg, then in a German
language school in Swakobmmont, where
the curriculum pushes a Christian
nationalist worldview and even paints
white South Africans as the real victims
of the region. This is where Peter Teal
spends formative years. It's a world
where his family benefits from a white
supremacist regime, where his father
actively advances its military
interests. A world where the founding
belief is that some people are meant to
rule and the majority must serve.
[music]
When Peter is 10, he and his family
return to the US. Peter's developing
into a classic nerd. He loves sci-fi and
fantasy, especially Lord of the Rings.
He's top of the class and becomes one of
the country's top chess players under
the age of 13. It's not cool to be a
nerd in the 70s and 80s, so Peter is
reportedly bullied on the regular,
but he knows he's smart and going
places. His chessboard has a sticker
that [music] says born to win. Peter
wants the best for himself, so he
studies hard to get into the top
university. At the time, Stanford is
ranked number one in the US. When he
makes it there in 1985, Stanford's a
huge letdown. Peter expects fellow
overachievers, but finds a party scene
instead. He'd rather hit the books than
the bong, and he's once again teased for
being a nerd. According to the author,
Max Chefkin, many of the students he
perceived as bullies also identify as
liberals, a connection that reportedly
sticks with him. We in fact asked here
ourselves, but didn't get a response.
Peter developed into a Reaganup
supporting conservative. The campus
itself feels far too left-wing for him.
Anti-Reagan and anti-aparttheide
protests are prominent and Peter starts
to clash with demonstrators. In the
contrarian, Chevkin describes how
classmates recall at least one instance
where Peter defended apart height as
economically sound. An allegation that
Teal has since denied.
At the time, some defenders of
aparttheight drew on libertarian
arguments. Libertarians believe the best
society maximizes personal and economic
freedom while minimizing government
control. They see free unregulated
markets as the best way to allocate
resources and drive innovation. More
radical libertarians value property
rights and free markets above basically
anything else. Critics say this leaves
little room for values like social
justice which are cast as secondary or
even incompatible with a libertarian
definition of freedom. From that
perspective, a part height could be
rationalized. South Africa's systematic
denial of civil rights was simply the
price to pay for its higher level of
wealth than neighboring countries. By
Peter's sophomore year, he's known on
campus as a hardcore libertarian. And
though the 80s sees students
increasingly advocate for race and
gender equality, Stanford is not an
entirely liberal institution. It has a
fair share of other conservative and
libertarian students and faculty members
during Peter's time there. Still, Chvkin
describes Peter feeling like he's in the
minority and that the dominant campus
culture is hostile to people like him.
So, he does what he'll keep doing
throughout his life. He builds a network
of like-minded men, [music] the
beginnings of a network that will
support him throughout his career, what
will later be known as the so-called
PayPal mafia.
With 11 other conservative men, Peter
launches a campus newspaper. The
Stanford Review aims to stir things up.
It regularly criticizes campus culture
from a conservative perspective with a
famously biting style. Throughout
Peter's time at Stanford, a few pieces
especially stirred a pot. Chefin found a
few examples in the Stanford archives
that he wasn't allowed to reproduce. One
columnist claimed that gay men engaged
in unnatural sex. Another complaint when
Stanford considered adding non-white
authors to the western culture course,
arguing it signaled the decline of the
West. One whole issue was devoted to
passionately defending a student accused
of statutory rape, who was later found
guilty. Peter's not just looking to
provoke. He wants money, power, and
influence. And as its founding
editor-inchief, the Stanford Review
launches him into the public
intellectual he's known as today. The
paper captures the attention of
high-profile conservatives, and a bit
later, Peter gets a book deal. The
diversity myth is co-authored with David
Sax, the student who wrote in defense of
an accused racist in the Stanford
Review. Nowadays, Sax is also an
influential figure on the American
right. He currently serves the Trump
administration as the White House's AI
and cryptozahar. The book argues that
universities are dangerous breeding
grounds for left-wing intellectual
conformity, that nowadays real racism
barely exists in America, and that
diversity initiatives pose a threat to
Western culture. Sex and Teal have since
apologized for some of the more
controversial parts of the book. But
these are the same anti-woke sentiments
that are winning elections today.
>> Immediately, you know, I ended woke
totally. Everything woke turns to
Our country will be woke no longer.
>> Though Peter has plenty of gripes about
Stanford, he stays on and graduates from
its law school in 1992. He moves to New
York to begin his legal career. Only
aiming for the best. His goal is to
clerk for the Supreme Court. He's got
top grades, his own influential paper,
and connections to the right people. But
it's not enough.
>> I got interviews with two justices. They
normally interview eight people and
select four as as clerks and I missed it
with both and it felt like uh it was the
absolute end of the world.
>> Peter's not used to setbacks. He plunges
into what he later described as a
quarterlife crisis and briefly moves
back in with his parents. But back on
the West Coast, Peter proves he has a
neck for turning losses into big wins.
[music] It's 1996. The tech industry is
booming. Silicon Valley is a place with
endless possibilities, loads of investor
money, and above all, unclear rules.
Peter wants in. Sure, he can't really
code, but he can hand that off on
someone else. Peter studies up on hedge
fund management, raises some capital,
and reinvents himself as an investor. At
the same time, he continues publishing
anti-woke columns. One that claims
Indigenous People's Day is anti-western
winds up in the Wall Street Journal. By
chance, Peter meets the brilliant young
cryptographer Max Leftchin. Max is
obsessed with Palm Pilots, clunky little
handheld computers. At the time, they're
barely more than a calendar with an
internet connection. Not all investors
would listen to a 20-some jabber away
about Palm Pilots, but Peter is not a
typical investor. Max believes Palm
Pilots will have way more potential if
they can be linked to businesses. If
personal devices were linked to a
business's infrastructure, a whole new
world of users would open up, like
connecting an individual directly with a
bank. All someone needs to figure out is
how to build an encrypted network that
can securely link a handheld device with
a corporate system. And Max believes he
can do it. He is way ahead of his time.
And Peter sees the potential
immediately. He offers Max a4 million
investment the very next day. Peter will
become known for these big bets on
inexperienced founders. Bats that very
often pay off.
On the surface, PayPal looks just like
another convenient way to pay. But in
reality, it was built on a radically
libertarian vision. Money moving freely
beyond government control. The same
vision that would later drive the crypto
movement. And just like crypto, that
freedom quickly attracts the gray areas
of the economy. PayPal's early growth
comes from industries most banks avoided
like gambling and NSFW stuff. Good thing
Peter's been nurturing his political
connections. As Chfkin tells it, Teal
worked to keep his business alive by
lobbying Congress to keep online
gambling legal and to stop PayPal from
being treated as a national bank. We
also asked Peter Teal directly about
this, but didn't get a response either.
E-commerce is exploding in popularity.
There's high demand for a tool that can
simplify online transaction. And Max and
Peter aren't the only ones working on a
solution. PayPal isn't even the only
online payment startup in the same
building. There's a very similar company
on the same floor. It's called X.com,
and its founder has a lot in common with
Peter. Most notably, Elon Musk is also
an enterprising immigrant with roots in
South Africa. Like Peter, he also shows
little regard for traditional rules of
the banking industry. Playing by every
rule only slows down growth. But for a
while, they have no idea what each
other's companies are for until a PayPal
employee finds a business plan for X.com
in a dumpster. And then it becomes
impossible to ignore each other. They
become two of the biggest fish in the
sea of online payments. PayPal's growing
rapidly, but at the same time bleeding
funds. Every new user gets a cash bonus.
Most transactions rack up fees and
servers are expensive. Worse, the
anonymity that makes PayPal attractive
also opens the door to credit card
fraud, and PayPal would have to refund
the victim's stolen money. Max left in
response by building an anti-fraud
system called Eigor, software that flex
suspicious patterns and blocks scam
transactions. All the while, user
anonymity is still preserved. Igor
successfully curbs fraud by half of what
it was. The FBI takes interest in the
technology and starts using the software
to catch money launderers.
Still, PayPal [music] isn't profitable.
Peter thinks he knows the answer. It has
to become [music] a monopoly. Eliminate
competitors, dominate the market, and
set the rules. As Peter often puts it,
competition is for losers. Competition
is for losers. Competition is for
losers.
>> This strategy will come to define Peter
Teal's success. He'll outline it in the
business best-selling book 0ero to one,
and it will become a guiding principle
in the tech industry. What I think
everybody who is a founder or
entrepreneur should aim to do is build a
monopoly and uh and all the great
companies [music] um that people have
built um are monopolies of one sort or
another. By 2000, the online payment
space has grown more competitive and
PayPal is still operating at a loss.
Elon suggests a merger and Peter agrees.
Uniting is their best chance for
survival.
According to the Contrarian, they clash
from the start, over the name, over the
software. Elon becomes CEO because he's
a bigger shareholder, but Peter
allegedly can't stand his leadership.
He's said to think Elon's a reckless
egoomaniac, and Elon is set to think
Peter's a sociopath who only cares about
money. Their battles stall the company's
growth. So, Teal decides to end them.
Elon goes on his honeymoon, leaving the
CEO position undefended. And in an
elegant, calculated move, Peter captures
it. Left and others loyal to Teal start
voicing their gripes about Musk. They
managed to convince enough board members
to oust Musk and to insert Teal as
temporary CEO, a position he'll keep. It
won't be Teal's last tactical takedown.
As CEO of PayPal, Peter Teal is on a
whole new playing field. In 2002, he
secures a landmark deal. eBay acquires
PayPal for $1.5 billion. Teal becomes a
multi-millionaire at 35 years old,
walking away with at least $55 million
from the deal. Now he has the capital
and credibility to pursue his wildest
dreams. The day he signs the deal is the
day he also steps down as CEO. PayPal
was just a stepping stone. Now he's
ready to move on to bigger and bolder
projects [music] and to live the high
life as a very rich person. He buys a
silver Ferrari and fancy apartments. Now
the formerly bullied kid is the life of
the party. More and more people want to
be in his orbit. Teal's personal
trajectory is skyrocketing,
but the country is spiraling.
In the wake of 9/11, Americans also face
a recession, an unpopular war, and
widespread trauma.
Teal is anxious, too. He's increasingly
concerned with the threat of religious
terrorism. He finds the Bush
administration isn't tough enough on
Islam. His politics seem to shift. At
Stanford, he wrote fiery libertarian
essays railing against government power.
Now he's arguing the opposite, that the
US must use extrajudicial methods to
catch terrorists, as he put it, outside
the checks and balances of
representative democracy as described in
high school textbooks. For Teal, the
trade-off is clear. The West must
compromise, more security, less freedom.
And he sees a business opportunity in
it. What if Igor, the software mix left
built to catch fraudsters, could be
retoled to catch terrorists? Wouldn't
the CIA be interested? In 2003, Teal
gets a team to start working on it right
away. They'll call the company
Palanteer.
In The Lord of the Rings, a Palanteer is
a mythical stone that sees and
communicates across far distances.
Sauron, the evil character who seeks to
dominate Middle Earth, uses a palanteer
to spy on enemies and conspire with
allies. The power of Eisenard is at your
command,
Sauron, Lord of the Earth.
>> Basically, Tal is offering Sauron's
power to anyone who can afford it.
Palanteer's promise, use network
analysis to find unforeseen patterns in
vast troughs of data. This is especially
interesting to US intelligence agencies
who had collected information on
al-Qaeda conspirators but failed to see
the connection till after the attack. In
the early years, many users are
disappointed with Palanteer's service.
But their timing is excellent with
everyone terrified of another attack.
And Teal's chosen CEO is excellent at
raising money. His name is Alex Corp.
He's another former Stanford classmate.
When Osama bin Laden is captured and
killed, rumors circulate that Palunteer
was used to find him. Public interest in
the company skyrockets. Based on what's
known today about Palanteer's abilities
at the time, any meaningful involvement
is questionable. When media outlets ask
Alex Kerp about that rumor, he's careful
not to confirm or deny involvement. He
tends to dodge the question with a smile
and imply that some connection is there.
>> Did your company helped to track and
kill
uh Osama bin Laden? When you open the
paper and look in the news about these
kind of things, there's a
twothirds chance, depending on the
country involved, that somehow my
company was involved. One media outlet
isn't buying the hype. A gossipy blog
called Gawker. According to Max Chefkin,
Gawker's Silicon Valley page reports no
real link between Palanteer and the Bin
Laden raid and suggests the company
spread the rumor just to boost sales.
Valleyweek is known for roasting the
tech industry back when most news
outlets tend to sing its praises. And a
favorite target of Gawker's gossip and
mockery is Peter Teio. Teal will take
care of Gawker later. Beyond founding
Palanteer, Teal spent the 2000s turning
tech startups into giants. I was the
sort of the first angel investor in
Facebook and summer of 2004. The
business was already tracking quite
well. They only needed money to buy more
computers. So I think that that was
always sort of a promising sign. In
2004, he becomes Facebook's first big
investor. Teal not only funds the
company, but becomes Zuckerberg's
mentor. Now Zuckerberg is one of the
richest people alive. And Teal's
investment will net him about $400
million. Teal doesn't stop there.
Through his network, he backs Airbnb,
Spotify, SpaceX, and later Open AI. In
2007, Teal seems to have spotted the
financial crisis early. He bets against
the US housing market. The gamble pays
off. A 60% return in just 6 months.
Banks will collapse and around 9 million
Americans will lose their jobs. But for
Teio, it's cause for celebration.
According to Chefkin, he flies his stuff
to Maui with unlimited taps for food,
booze, massages, and surfing. We asked
Peter Teal if this is true, but he
didn't answer. But Teal's golden run
doesn't last. After a string of bad
investments and mass redemptions, his
hedge fund suffers huge losses and all
but collapses. By 2011, he will have
lost nearly 2/3 of his client's money.
The crisis seems to make Teal more
cynical. In 2009, he writes that he
still believes in libertarian
principles, but no longer in democracy.
I no longer believe that freedom and
democracy are compatible, he declares.
He argues that America has been in
decline since the 1920s when women
gained the right to vote and when the
Great Depression created mass
unemployment. In his view, women and
poor people are especially hostile to
libertarian policies. Their ability to
vote stands in the way of his ideal
society. The essay makes waves. Gawker
media calls him a loopy libertarian,
ridiculing him for wishing women
couldn't vote. Tier later clarifies it's
not that he wants to take one class of
voters rights away. The problem is that
Americans in general won't vote for
libertarian policies.
So better to do away with democracy
altogether.
Meanwhile, Gawka media gleefully reports
Teal's investment failures. They claim
he exaggerates his net worth and make
fun of his hypocrisies. Gawker reported
on a lot of important topics other media
outlets wouldn't touch till much later,
like the crimes of Harvey Weinstein and
Jeffrey Epstein, but they also posted a
lot of arguably cruel gossip. In 2007,
they outed teal sexual orientation with
a post titled Peter Teal is totally gay
people. Peter Teal's sexuality was an
open secret at the time, but he didn't
seem to want it reported. His outing was
clearly a violation of privacy.
According to the contrarian, Tiel sees
Gawker's coverage as damaging to his
business, and plenty of other people
have grudges against the site. So, Tio
quietly funds a team of lawyers to take
up their cases. The decisive moment
comes in 2012 when Gawker publishes a
leaked sex tape of the wrestler Hulk
Hogan. Hogan sues and Teal secretly
bankrolls the fight with $10 million.
Hogan.
>> The stage is set for a major courtroom
battle. Hulk Hogan, former professional
wrestler turned reality star, is taking
on media website Gawker.
>> Gawker is hit with just over $140
million in damages and files for
bankruptcy in 2016. Gawker Media is no
more, and Teal is proud of his win,
calling it the most philanthropic thing
he's ever done. In an interview, he
compares the journalists behind the
company to terrorists. The world learned
that it's dangerous to mess with Peter
Teal. Reporters Without Borders called
his feet a serious threat on freedom of
the press. Critics argue that this set a
precedent for wealthy individuals to
weaponize the courts and bury media that
criticizes them.
But Peter Teal is just getting started.
It's [music] often said that two things
in life are certain, death
[clears throat] and taxes. Well, Peter
Teal disagrees. What others see as
inevitabilities, Teal sees as problems
to be solved. He famously funds biotech
companies pursuing life extension. His
hatred of taxes hasn't poor resources
into anti-ax political actions and also
seasteading, man-made island nations
free from income tax and governmental
regulations. a floating libertarian
utopia where he can escape systems he
finds oppressive, an idea he has since
abandoned. He looks into other exit
plans like a bunker in New Zealand,
which he also later drops, and the
chance for humanity to reach Mars. This
becomes Peter Thiel's pattern, seeking
escape. Escape from rules that govern
everyone else.
But escape on Peter Teal's scale doesn't
come easily. Immortality research and
space exploration require massive
resources. Changing tax laws requires
massive influence. Fortunately for Tio,
his wealth and influence have grown
enormously. So he can attempt to reshape
politics to enable his search for
escape.
In 2007, he does something unusual for
Silicon Valley entrepreneurs. He starts
funding presidential candidates. His
first big bet is the libertarian Ron
Paul. A longshot candidate for
presidency, but a politician with a
passionate base. Like Tio, Paul is an
advocate for extreme free market
capitalism. They're also both skeptical
of climate change to different degrees.
Ron Paul doesn't win the 2008
presidency. Obama does. In 2012, Ron
Paul runs again. And this time, Teal is
his biggest donor by a long shot. Teal
wasn't really banking on Paul's win.
Instead, he was thinking ahead. In an
interview with the magazine Slate from
2012, Teal says he was really
campaigning for 2016, building up a
strong libertarian base.
Teal seems to want a candidate who will
ensure his wealth will be protected, one
who will grant more power to the tech
industry, and one who shares his view
that America is in decline and needs a
strong man to become great again. When
Trump is revealed as the best candidate
to promote those aims, Teal donates
$1.25 million to his campaign. In 2016,
Teal takes the stage at the Republican
National Convention during prime time.
Tonight, I urge all of my fellow
Americans to stand up and vote for
Donald Trump.
>> Teal campaigns for Trump as if his views
represented Silicon Valley. But at the
time, Trump is deeply unpopular in tech.
Of the top tech companies in the valley,
not a single CEO donates to Trump's 2016
campaign, and Teal's support of Trump
makes him somewhat of a pariah.
According to the Contrarian, friends cut
ties with him or refuse to discuss
politics. Teal is unbothered. They'll
change their tune soon enough. Besides,
he's starting to lean into his image as
the Silicon Valley super villain. He
reportedly once said, "I'd rather be
seen as evil than incompetent." When
Trump shocks the world by winning, Teal
is part of the transition team. His role
is to appoint people who will disrupt
regulatory bodies like the Federal Trade
Commission and the Food and Drug
Administration. A dream job for Teal,
who's railed against governmental
regulation for decades. Teal reportedly
suggests 150 names to Trump. According
to Max Chefkin, his list includes to, no
surprise, ultra libertarians, but also
very controversial figures, fringe
people from his growing network of
far-right reactionaries. Trump only
approves a handful of them, the least
controversial suggestions that Teal
makes. So Teal's first attempt at
capturing the White House seems to have
failed. Politically, Teal retreats to
the background for a bit. He and his
partner have their first child and he
seems to focus on family life for a
while. But the background is where Peter
Teal thrives the most.
Outside of politics, Teal's businesses
are skyrocketing, especially Palanteer.
During CO, Palanteer wins government
contracts to analyze pandemic data,
tracking infections and vaccines. In
2025, Business Insider reports that
under the second Trump administration,
ICC will use Palanteer to track down
immigrants who overstate their visas.
Palanteer's involvement has only
intensified under Trump and has been
instrumental for over a decade since
Obama's second administration. The
Guardian reports in 2025 that Palanteer
provides ICE with tools that help their
agents fulfill Trump's aggressive
deportation quotas using a vast data
network. It includes government records
such as text data from the IRS and
private databases like location history
from cell phone records. Now, Palanteer
also incorporates facial recognition
data from Clear View AI, another startup
where Peter Teal is the first investor.
The pattern is clear. Palanteer thrives
in chaos and chaos is only ramping up.
What looks like a political setback with
Trump may just be Tiel's chance to plan
his next move. Teal won't back Trump's
second campaign, but he will build up
another politician.
>> We're effectively run in this country
via the Democrats, via via our corporate
oligarchs, by a bunch of childless cat
ladies who are miserable at their own
lives and the choices that they've made.
Teal injects JD Vance's primary campaign
with $15 million. Vance is now vice
president of the United States. Teal and
Vance's relationship didn't come out of
nowhere. Vance worked at one of Teal's
companies and Teal became his mentor, as
Vance himself says. And it was also Teal
who brought JD Vance and Donald Trump
together.
After Trump is elected as president
again in 2024, several members of the
tech elite rally behind him. There's
Elon Musk, who is against Trump in 2016
and becomes his most visible supporter
in 2024. There's Mark Zuckerberg, who
abolishes fact checkers at Matter less
than two weeks before Trump takes
office. And there's Sunda Pikai, the CEO
of Google, who donates $1 million to
Trump just before inauguration.
At the inauguration of Trump's second
presidency in January 2025, major tech
CEOs are clearly visible in the front
row. But one person isn't there that
day.
He's in the background again, Peter
Teal. Instead, he watches Palanteer
stock skyrocket and topping the market
for much of 2025. The surge is in part
fueled by government contracts. And not
just in the US. Palanteer has been hired
by Israeli forces, allegedly to enable
AI powered targeting of Palestinians,
which the company denies, and by Ukraine
in its war against Russia. These and
other contracts not only boost
Palunteer's profits, they also give the
company access to extremely sensitive
data. Few assets carry more power or
more potential for harm. So, who decides
how it's used?
We reached out to Peter Teal as well as
Palanteer because we had a lot of
questions. Unfortunately, none of them
were answered.
In 2012, Peter Teio said, "One of the
things I like about technology is that
when technology is unregulated, you can
change the world without getting
approval from other people. At its best,
it's not subject to democratic control
and not subject to the majority, which I
think is often hostile to change. A
recent venture Teal backed is called
Arabore, a crypto bank named after the
mountain in the Hobbit, where a
murderous dragon hordes treasure. And
now Trump is pushing one of Teal's
wilder ideas, low tax freedom cities
where corporations can operate without
federal regulations.
>> We'll actually build new cities in our
country again. These freedom cities will
reopen the frontier, reignite American
imagination.
>> Freedom cities aren't just for making a
lot of money. The goal is also to
conduct research without governmental
approval. One such place already exists,
Prospera in Honduras. You already know
who helped fund it. The libertarian
utopia Peter Teal dreams of no longer
needs Mars or the open ocean. It's being
built right in [music] America.